Guide to the Vernon R. Stedman Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Vernon R. Stedman Papers
1933-1972
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections
4661
4661-001
Stedman, Vernon R.
1.21 cubic feet 2 boxes
Papers of a Seattle labor official and labor historian
Vernon R. Stedman (1916-1993) was a National Labor Bureau researcher and labor negotiator for maritime unions. In the 1950s he studied economics at the University of Washington, and conducted research for a dissertation tentatively entitled "Development of Collective Bargaining in the Puget Sound Inland Waterways Industry." The project dealt largely with the history of the Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific (IBU), but also to some extent the Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association (MEBA) and the Masters, Mates and Pilots (MMP). In his research he consulted with John M. Fox, who became Business Manager and President of the IBU after also serving with the MMP, and with Clyde W. Deal, who helped form the IBU and who went on to work in the United States Department of Labor's Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service. Stedman did not complete his dissertation.
The collection is organized into three subgroups:
Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific, 1933-1961
National Labor Bureau Seattle Office, 1947-1959
Personal Papers, 1940-1972
Vernon Stedman's papers consist primarily of drafts of dissertation chapters in varying stages of completion, as well as materials which Stedman collected, presumably for use in writing his dissertation. The IBU subgroup contains correspondence between John M. Fox and Clyde W. Deal, as well as a large number of labor agreements and wage scales. The subgroup also contains scattered materials from both MMP and MEBA, and materials that concern more than one union such as jointly-negotiated agreements. The National Labor Bureau subgroup includes records of and exhibits from proceedings on behalf of MEBA, as well as reports and other writings not clearly related to Stedman's dissertation. Personal Papers contains dissertation chapter drafts, fragments and research notes, a transcript of an interview Stedman conducted with Clyde W. Deal in 1955, and notes from an interview with Ralph Goldsmith, also affiliated with the IBU. Also present are Stedman's coursework, and several subject files covering topics which Stedman documented primarily through newspaper clippings. Folders containing dissertation chapters have been kept in original order and often include fragments, notes, revisions and related material. In several of the chapters, the most complete draft as assembled by Stedman is followed by a folder with other drafts, fragments or revisions.
Major correspondents include Clyde W. Deal, John M. Fox and economist Robert J. Lampman.
Open to all users.
Donated by Winifred Stedman in 2003.
Stedman, Vernon R.$vArchives; Deal, Clyde W.$vCorrespondence; Fox, John M.,$d1902-1978$vCorrespondence; Inland Boatmen's Union of the Pacific.; International Organization of Masters, Mates, and Pilots; National Labor Bureau. Seattle Office; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Merchant mariners$xLabor unions$xResearch$zPacific Coast (North America); Labor movement$xResearch$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Correspondence; Dissertations; Drafts (documents); Transcripts; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Interviews
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor; Labor history; Labor unions; Ships and Shipping; Wasington (State); Seattle; Labor History
- Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific, 1933-1961
  - Historical Features, circa 1937 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - General Correspondence
    - Between John M. Fox and Clyde W. Deal, 1940-1951 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1933-1940 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Intraorganizational Correspondence, 1940-1959 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Reports: President's Report, 1936 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Agreements and Wage Scales, 1947-1961 (Box-folder 1/6-10)
  - Subject File: Disaffiliation with Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1947 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Speeches and Writings of Others, 1940, 1950 (Box-folder 1/12-15)
  - Ephemera, circa 1951 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Clippings, 1956 (Box-folder 1/17)
- National Labor Bureau Seattle Office., 1947-1959
  - Speeches and Writings, undated (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Proceedings
    - Arbitration Proceeding between Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association, Local No. 38, and Puget Sound Navigation Company, 1948 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Arbitration Proceeding between Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association, Local No. 38, and Puget Sound Navigation Company, 1949 (Box-folder 1/20)
      Exhibits only.
  - Hearings: Labor-Management Problems of the American Merchant Marine, 1955 (Box-folder 1/21)
    Before the United States House of Representatives Committee on the Merchant Marine and Fisheries
  - Reports
    - Report on the Investigation of the Earnings, Property, Operations, Rates, Services and Facilities of the Puget Sound Navigation Company, 1947 (Box-folder 1/22)
      Prepared by the Accounting Section, Department of Transportation, State of Washington
    - Analytical Report on Puget Sound Navigation, Incorporated, 1949 (Box-folder 1/23)
      Prepared by Dun and Bradstreet
    - Waterborne Foreign Statistical Report: Imports and Exports, Port of Seattle, 1955 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Federal Responsibility for Medical Care of Seamen (C.J. Simpson, National Labor Bureau), 1954 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Subject Files
    - Alaska Canned Salmon Industry, 1945, undated (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Seattle Halibut Fleet, 1957-1959, undated (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Negotiations and Agreements, 1958 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Notes, 1954, undated (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box-folder 1/30)
- Personal Papers, 1940-1972
  - General Correspondence: regarding dissertation, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Interview Transcript: Clyde W. Deal, 1955 (Box-folder 1/32)
  - Interview Notes: Ralph Goldsmith, 1958 (Box-folder 1/33)
  - Speeches and Writings
    - Dissertation: "Development of Collective Bargaining in the Puget Sound Inland Waterways Industry" (working title)
      Numbers in parentheses are Stedman's chapter numbers.
      - Outlines and Research Notes, undated (Box-folder 1/34)
      - Fragments, Unidentified Page and Table Drafts, undated (Box-folder 1/35)
      - Material for Untitled Chapter (2), undated (Box-folder 1/36)
      - "Origins of Ferryboatmen's Union of California" (3), undated (Box-folder 1/37)
      - "The Organizing Drive on Puget Sound" (5), undated (Box-folder 1/38-39)
      - "The Drive for Recognition" (6), undated (Box-folder 1/40-41)
      - "The NRA [National Recovery Administration] Period" (7), undated (Box-folder 1/42-43)
      - "Collective Bargaining Begins" (8), undated (Box-folder 2/1-2)
      - "The British Columbia Organizing Drive" (8a), undated (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Untitled Chapter (15), undated (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Untitled Chapter (16), undated (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 2/6-8)
  - Speeches and Writings of Others, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Subject Files
    - Black Ball Line, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Freight Boats, 1954, 1956 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - "PSN [Puget Sound Navigation Company] Rates & Feb 4? strike", 1940-1949, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Puget Sound Maritime Historical Society, 1959 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - "UMW [United Mine Workers Local] #50 Raid", 1956-1957 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Washington State Ferries, 1955-1959, undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Clippings, 1960-1961, 1970, 1972 (Box-folder 2/16)